<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Ted&#39;s notes</title>
    <link>http://tedhagos.com/categories/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Ted&#39;s notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright Ted Hagos</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 19:18:23 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://tedhagos.com/categories/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Cheatsheet</title>
      <link>http://tedhagos.com/posts/linux-cheatsheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2014 19:18:23 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tedhagos.com/posts/linux-cheatsheet/</guid>
      <description>Copy pasting clipboard to/from terminal Can be done either via xsel or xclip. Xclip is part of most modern installations, so you it may be there in your installation already. The common usages are:
You copied something in an X window (browser or editor etc), you want to paste the content to the terminal. Unfortunately the terminal doesn&amp;rsquo;t have access to the clipboard. But you can do this on the terminal using</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SMS messages using USB Modem</title>
      <link>http://tedhagos.com/posts/send-receive-sms-usb-modem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2011 08:10:54 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tedhagos.com/posts/send-receive-sms-usb-modem/</guid>
      <description>This guide uses gnokii-sms to send and receive SMS messages using Linux PC. The project I was working on did not require industrial grade throughput. That is the reason I cannot justify the cost of WaveComm iTegra type equipment. The SMS project was ran on a Debian Linux. If you are using a different distro, use the packaging mechanism of your distro.
There were a couple of other solution approaches but I went for gnokii-sms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux Command Line</title>
      <link>http://tedhagos.com/posts/linux-command-line/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2011 16:01:22 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tedhagos.com/posts/linux-command-line/</guid>
      <description> Environment  Vagrant Raspberry Pi; or An Actual Linux machine  cmd Line Text Files File Management cmd Line Streams and Pipes Processes Regular Expressions Vim </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>