<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-20T01:23:02+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ted Hagos</title><subtitle>coder, trainer and author</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Case for Boring Tech: Why Stability is a Feature</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/engineering/strategy/2026/01/20/the-boring-tech-why-stability-is-a-feature.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Case for Boring Tech: Why Stability is a Feature" /><published>2026-01-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2026-01-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/engineering/strategy/2026/01/20/the-boring-tech-why-stability-is-a-feature</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/engineering/strategy/2026/01/20/the-boring-tech-why-stability-is-a-feature.html"><![CDATA[<p>We have a persistent problem in software engineering: we frequently confuse “novelty” with “value.” Every six months, a new framework arrives that promises to solve all the problems of the previous framework—which was itself considered the “solution” just a year ago. It is tempting to think that staying on the cutting edge is the only way to remain relevant in this industry.</p>

<p>However, if you are building a product that needs to function reliably three years from now, “interesting” technology is a liability. In this context, <strong>“boring” technology is a significant competitive advantage.</strong></p>

<h2 id="the-innovation-token-system">The Innovation Token System</h2>

<p>Think of your project as having a strictly limited budget of <strong>three Innovation Tokens.</strong> This isn’t just a metaphor; it is a mental model for managing the total amount of complexity your team can handle before the system becomes unmanageable.</p>

<p>Every time you choose a database that is only two years old, or a programming language that has not yet reached a stable version 1.0, you spend a token. If you spend all three tokens on your infrastructure—the foundation of your app—you have zero tokens left to spend on the actual problem you are trying to solve for your users.</p>

<p>Boring technology consists of things like Postgres, Java, or Linux. These are “solved” problems. They do not require innovation tokens because their behavior is well-documented, and their “surprises” have already been discovered by someone else. When you use Postgres, you aren’t innovating on how data is stored; you are using a tool that has survived thirty years of edge cases. This leaves your tokens available for the things that actually matter: your unique business logic and your user experience.</p>

<h2 id="the-mathematics-of-the-bus-factor">The Mathematics of the Bus Factor</h2>

<p>In engineering, we use a risk metric called the <strong>Bus Factor.</strong> This is the minimum number of team members who would have to be hit by a bus (or suddenly quit) before a project stalls because nobody else knows how the system works.</p>

<p>When you use a niche, experimental functional language or a brand-new “serverless” framework that only two people on Earth truly understand, your Bus Factor is effectively one. If that person leaves, the project enters a state of “archaeological maintenance,” where the remaining team spends more time deciphering the intent of the code than actually shipping features.</p>

<h3 id="knowledge-distribution-vs-syntax-specialization">Knowledge Distribution vs. Syntax Specialization</h3>

<p>When you choose a “boring” stack, you are choosing a massive, global talent pool. Skills like SQL or REST are “commodity knowledge.” You can hire a replacement on a Tuesday, and they can be making meaningful contributions by Thursday because the patterns are universal.</p>

<p>Experimental tech requires “bespoke knowledge.” You must first find the rare candidate who knows the tech, then wait months as they learn your specific implementation of its unpolished quirks. High novelty tech creates high friction for hiring; boring tech creates a low-friction environment where new people can become productive almost immediately.</p>

<h2 id="the-unholy-hour-test">The Unholy Hour Test</h2>

<p>Everything breaks eventually. The primary advantage of boring technology is that we have a very good idea of exactly <em>how</em> it breaks. We understand its memory leaks, its scaling limits, and its specific quirks.</p>

<h3 id="1-the-search-engine-advantage">1. The Search Engine Advantage</h3>
<p>When boring tech breaks during “unholy hours”—those inconvenient times in the middle of the night—someone else has almost certainly already found the fix and posted it online. If your database stops responding at 3:00 AM, you want to find a Stack Overflow thread from 2014 that explains exactly which configuration flag to flip.</p>

<h3 id="2-researcher-vs-developer">2. Researcher vs. Developer</h3>
<p>When “cutting-edge” technology breaks, you are no longer just a developer; you are a primary researcher. You aren’t just fixing a bug; you are discovering a new property of an unstable system. Discovery is great for science, but it is terrible for a production environment that needs to be online 24/7. In production, “discovery” is just a fancy word for “unplanned downtime.”</p>

<h3 id="3-predictable-failure">3. Predictable Failure</h3>
<p>A mature system like the Linux kernel or the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) has been tested by millions of users across billions of hours of runtime. Its failure modes are documented. A new framework, however, might fail in a way the creators never even imagined. In software, “unpredictable” is a synonym for “expensive.”</p>

<h2 id="the-hype-cycle-trap">The Hype Cycle Trap</h2>

<p>Most new technologies follow what we call the <strong>Hype Cycle.</strong> There is a “Peak of Inflated Expectations,” followed by a “Trough of Disillusionment” when developers realize the new tool doesn’t actually solve everything.</p>

<p>Boring tech has already made it through this cycle. It has reached the “Plateau of Productivity.” When you choose a tool at the peak of its hype, you are essentially gambling that the tool will mature faster than your project needs to scale. This is rarely a winning bet. Boring tech optimizes for the “staying in business” phase rather than the “getting started” phase.</p>

<h2 id="choosing-your-battles">Choosing Your Battles</h2>

<p>Choosing boring technology does not mean being a “dinosaur” or refusing to learn. It means being strategic with your energy. Your users do not care if you used a revolutionary, experimental graph database. They care that the checkout page works every single time they click the button.</p>

<p>As a Senior Engineer, your primary job is to <strong>manage risk.</strong> The greatest risk to a project is often the “exciting” technology you chose at the very beginning when you were feeling optimistic. If you want to innovate, innovate on your product. Keep the foundation boring.</p>

<h2 id="build-something-that-lasts">Build Something That Lasts</h2>

<p>I spent a long time in software development watching frameworks come and go. The systems we built ten years ago that are still running today all have one thing in common: they were built on boring foundations. They don’t require weekly babysitting or constant rewrites to stay compatible with the latest “hot” library. They just work.</p>

<p>Build for the long haul. Spend your innovation tokens on your customers, not on your database. Keep your foundation boring, so your results can be extraordinary.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ted Hagos</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><category term="Strategy" /><category term="Software Engineering" /><category term="System Architecture" /><category term="Web Development" /><category term="DevOps" /><category term="Postgres" /><category term="Java" /><category term="Career Advice" /><category term="Scalability" /><category term="Risk Management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have a persistent problem in software engineering: we frequently confuse “novelty” with “value.” Every six months, a new framework arrives that promises to solve all the problems of the previous framework—which was itself considered the “solution” just a year ago. It is tempting to think that staying on the cutting edge is the only way to remain relevant in this industry.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving Past Junior: How to Stop Stressing and Start Growing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/career-growth/2026/01/20/moving-past-junior-how-to-stop-stressing-and-start-growing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving Past Junior: How to Stop Stressing and Start Growing" /><published>2026-01-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2026-01-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/career-growth/2026/01/20/moving-past-junior-how-to-stop-stressing-and-start-growing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/career-growth/2026/01/20/moving-past-junior-how-to-stop-stressing-and-start-growing.html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re a Junior dev, you’re probably living in a constant state of “I hope I don’t break the entire company today”. You’re the one staring at a Pull Request for forty minutes before hitting “Submit,” wondering if your variable names are stupid or if you missed something obvious that’s going to make the Senior devs sigh.</p>

<p>First, take a breath: We all feel like that. I’ve written tech books for Apress, and I still have moments where I stare at a CSS bug and wonder if I should have just been a carpenter.</p>

<p>The difference between a Junior and a Mid-level dev isn’t that the Mid-level knows everything—it’s just that they have a system for when things go sideways. Moving to that “Mid-level” spot isn’t about suddenly becoming a genius; it’s about being reliable. It’s about your lead knowing that if they give you a task, they don’t have to stay up late double-checking your work.</p>

<p>Here is how you actually make that jump without burning yourself out.</p>

<h2 id="1-dont-just-throw-the-error-over-the-fence">1. Don’t Just Throw the Error Over the Fence</h2>
<p>We’ve all been there. You hit a bug, you’ve been staring at it for an hour, and you’re stuck. A Junior dev usually just says: “Hey, this isn’t working. Can you help?”. When you do that, you’re basically asking the Senior dev to do your job for you.</p>

<p>If you want to move up, you need to change how you ask for help. Show them the map of where you’ve already walked. Try this instead:</p>

<p>“Hey, I’m stuck on this API call. I’ve checked the logs, I tested the endpoint in Postman, and I tried changing the header, but I’m still getting a 403. I think it’s an auth issue. What am I missing?”</p>

<p>Now, you aren’t just a “task-taker”. You’re a collaborator. You’ve done the legwork, and you’re just asking for a nudge in the right direction. That’s what Mid-level devs do.</p>

<h2 id="2-the-dont-make-me-think-pull-request">2. The “Don’t Make Me Think” Pull Request</h2>
<p>If I’m your Senior dev and I open your Pull Request, I should be able to understand what you did in about thirty seconds. If your PR is a giant mess of 50 changed files with a description that just says “fixed stuff,” you’re making me do extra work. And if I have to do extra work, I’m going to think you aren’t ready for more responsibility.</p>

<p>Mid-level devs make life easy for their reviewers:</p>

<p>They write a few bullet points explaining why they changed what they changed.</p>

<p>They leave a comment on their own code if something looks a bit weird, explaining the trade-off they made.</p>

<p>Basically, you’re trying to prevent me from having to ask “Why did you do this?”.</p>

<p>If I don’t have to ask that, you’ve passed the test.</p>

<h2 id="3-stop-chasing-the-perfect-code">3. Stop Chasing the “Perfect” Code</h2>
<p>Juniors tend to fall into two camps: they either write “spaghetti” just to make it work, or they spend three days trying to make one function “perfect” and “elegant”. Real-world coding is about balance. You need to ship.</p>

<p>Mid-level devs understand that “Good and Shipped” is better than “Perfect and Never Done”. They know that the code they write today might need to be changed in six months, so they focus on making it easy to delete. If your code is simple and modular, it doesn’t have to be a masterpiece. It just has to be clear enough that the next person can fix it without needing a map and a flashlight.</p>

<h2 id="4-own-your-mistakes-theyre-going-to-happen">4. Own Your Mistakes (They’re Going to Happen)</h2>
<p>You will break the build. You will accidentally delete a row in a dev database. You will ship a typo to production.</p>

<p>A Junior dev tries to hide it or hopes nobody notices. A Mid-level dev is the first person in the Slack channel saying: “Hey, I think I just broke the staging environment. I’m looking into it now, here’s what happened”. I would much rather work with a developer who breaks things and owns it than a “genius” who hides their tracks. Reliability isn’t about being perfect; it’s about being the person who stays to help clean up the mess.</p>

<h2 id="5-start-asking-why">5. Start Asking “Why?”</h2>
<p>When you get a ticket that says “Add a checkbox here,” don’t just add the checkbox. Ask: “Wait, why are we adding this? Is it for a specific user request?”. Sometimes, you’ll realize that the checkbox doesn’t actually solve the user’s problem.</p>

<p>When you start thinking about the product and not just the code, you’ve officially stopped being a “Junior”. You’re starting to see the big picture. That’s the exact moment people start treating you like a Senior-in-training.</p>

<p>I’ve spent a long time helping devs get out of the “Junior” rut. It’s not about learning a new framework every weekend. It’s about building the right habits so you can go home at 5:00 PM without worrying about your code falling apart.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ted Hagos</name></author><category term="career-growth" /><category term="Career Advice" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you’re a Junior dev, you’re probably living in a constant state of “I hope I don’t break the entire company today”. You’re the one staring at a Pull Request for forty minutes before hitting “Submit,” wondering if your variable names are stupid or if you missed something obvious that’s going to make the Senior devs sigh.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Complexity Tax: Calculating the True Cost of Your Kubernetes Cluster</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/devops/architecture/2026/01/16/the-complexity-tax-kubernetes-cost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Complexity Tax: Calculating the True Cost of Your Kubernetes Cluster" /><published>2026-01-16T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2026-01-16T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/devops/architecture/2026/01/16/the-complexity-tax-kubernetes-cost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/devops/architecture/2026/01/16/the-complexity-tax-kubernetes-cost.html"><![CDATA[<p>Engineering teams often reach the same conclusion: “We should move this to Kubernetes.” It sounds like progress. Usually, it’s just a debt trap.</p>

<p>Maturity in software isn’t about using the most powerful tools. It’s about realizing that every choice carries a cost you keep paying long after the excitement of the “new toy” fades. Kubernetes solves real problems, but it charges a <strong>Complexity Tax</strong> that doesn’t appear on your cloud bill.</p>

<h3 id="the-hidden-bill">The Hidden Bill</h3>
<p>Your cloud provider gives you a tidy invoice for virtual machines, load balancers, and storage. You look at the total and think it’s affordable.</p>

<p>The real costs are hidden in <strong>Cognitive Load</strong>. They appear in:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Slack threads</strong> that last four hours because a network rule changed and six senior engineers are trying to figure out which of the three overlapping policies is currently lying to them.</li>
  <li><strong>Onboarding sessions</strong> where new hires realize they need to learn five new abstractions just to deploy a “Hello World” app.</li>
  <li><strong>The “Maintenance Black Hole”:</strong> Time spent fixing the platform instead of building features for customers.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="1-operational-labor-the-maintenance-sinkhole">1. Operational Labor: The Maintenance Sinkhole</h3>
<p>Kubernetes doesn’t remove the need for maintenance; it just shifts it. Instead of updating a server, you are now managing “version skew”—ensuring your cluster version matches your tool version—and “Helm charts,” which are massive, nested configuration files that are easy to break and hard to read.</p>

<p>The result is that you didn’t eliminate operations work; you just turned every developer into a part-time systems administrator. You are now paying senior developer salaries for people to spend 30% of their week arguing with a container orchestrator.</p>

<h3 id="2-the-abstraction-wall">2. The Abstraction Wall</h3>
<p>Every system has a “mental model”—the amount of information an engineer has to hold in their head to understand how a request gets from a user to the database.</p>

<p>In a simple setup, you have a Server and your App. In Kubernetes, you have Pods, Nodes, Deployments, Services, Ingress, and ConfigMaps. To a user, your app is a website. To Kubernetes, your app is a sprawling legal dispute between twelve different configuration files.</p>

<p>When a bug appears, engineers stop debugging the actual code. They start debugging the <em>layers around</em> the code. Nothing “crashes” with a clear error; it just fails to connect, and you have to check six different places to find out why.</p>

<h3 id="3-yaml-archaeology-and-the-local-dev-tax">3. YAML Archaeology and the Local Dev Tax</h3>
<p>As the system grows, the configuration files (YAML) become historical artifacts. No one remembers why a specific resource limit or affinity rule was set in 2023, but everyone is too afraid to delete it because the last person who tried broke the production staging environment for a week. We have reached the era of <strong>YAML Archaeology</strong>, where we treat infrastructure code like ancient runes that shouldn’t be disturbed.</p>

<p>Furthermore, there is the <strong>Local Development Tax</strong>. To work on the app, developers now need to run a “mini-cluster” on their laptops. If your development environment requires 16GB of RAM just to sit idle while it simulates a cloud environment, you haven’t built a tool; you’ve built a space heater that occasionally compiles code.</p>

<h3 id="4-distributed-failure">4. Distributed Failure</h3>
<p>Simple systems fail in obvious ways. Complex systems fail in “quiet” ways. If a single server dies, the site is down, and you fix the server.</p>

<p>In Kubernetes, a service might look “healthy” in the dashboard while being unable to talk to the database because of a tiny error in a network policy. It takes much longer to fix things—not because the engineers aren’t smart, but because there are too many layers for a bug to hide in. We have traded “Down Time” for “Ghost Time”—periods where the system is technically running but functionally broken in ways that are nearly impossible to trace.</p>

<h3 id="a-boring-tco-model">A Boring TCO Model</h3>
<p><strong>Total Cost = Cloud Invoice + Engineering Salaries + Lost Velocity.</strong></p>

<p>If Kubernetes requires you to hire one extra senior engineer just to keep the lights on, or if it eats 20% of your team’s focus every week, it isn’t “efficient”. You are simply spending your salary budget on infrastructure management instead of product growth.</p>

<h3 id="the-reality-check">The Reality Check</h3>
<p>Before migrating, answer these without using the words “eventually” or “industry standard”:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Scale:</strong> Do we have 5 services or 500? If it’s 5, you don’t need a cluster.</li>
  <li><strong>Ownership:</strong> When the site lags, who is the <em>one</em> person who can trace the traffic through the mesh? Do they ever get to take a vacation?</li>
  <li><strong>Growth:</strong> Are we expecting 10x more users, or just 10x more features? Kubernetes helps with users; it often slows down features.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-alternative-the-boring-stack">The Alternative: The “Boring” Stack</h3>
<p>The goal isn’t to have the most “modern” system; it’s to have the cheapest system that solves today’s problems.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>The Small Setup:</strong> Use a virtual machine (VM) and a simple system service to restart your app if it crashes. It’s boring, it’s cheap, and any junior dev can understand it in ten minutes.</li>
  <li><strong>The Middle Ground:</strong> Use “Managed Container” services like AWS Fargate or Google Cloud Run. You get the benefits of containers without the tax of managing the “engine” yourself.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h3>
<p>The “boring stack” wins because it’s easy to understand and cheap to fix. The best system is the one your team can explain on a whiteboard from memory, without needing to open six browser tabs to remember how the networking works.</p>

<p>If your infrastructure requires a <strong>permanent life-support team</strong> just to keep it breathing, you haven’t built a tool; you’ve built a liability. Build something that can survive a weekend without you. Build something boring instead.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ted Hagos</name></author><category term="DevOps" /><category term="Architecture" /><category term="Kubernetes" /><category term="Cloud Computing" /><category term="Software Engineering" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Kubernetes is a powerful tool, but it comes with a hidden bill. Learn why the 'Complexity Tax' might be costing your team more than your cloud invoice.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The changing role of QA in an Agile environment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sdlc/2019/07/22/qa-role-in-agile.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The changing role of QA in an Agile environment" /><published>2019-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sdlc/2019/07/22/qa-role-in-agile</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sdlc/2019/07/22/qa-role-in-agile.html"><![CDATA[<p>Software testing remains a very important and integral part of software development. Before the advent of Agile practices, software testing was, an afterthought; it’s something that we do right after coding finishes. We’ve come a long way from that. Some teams even write the tests first, before writing the actual codes. The tests not only serve as a gatekeeper for releases, but more importantly, they also serve as an important documentation for the code.</p>

<p>It has been two decades since the Agile manifesto was published, and we spent the good part of it trying to figure out how testers fit into this new paradigm; we are still figuring it out, but we have gotten better. Part of the reason we got better is because the tools have gotten better. The proliferation of automated testing techniques has immensely helped us transition from waterfall to the highly iterative Agile practice.</p>

<p>A key reason why high-performing teams have succeeded in adopting Agile practices is because the roles within the development team have shifted. Nowadays, everyone tests.</p>

<p>A typical Agile team is composed of 3-6 developers, a product owner, a SCRUM master and a QA engineer. We no longer use an army of testers to bookend the development process. As the team matures, everyone becomes more and more cross-functional. Everybody becomes a tester. Functional testing is no longer the exclusive province the QA engineer; this has become the task of the developer. The advancement of testing frameworks and the team being more cross-functional, makes it possible for functional testing to occur at a point very close to requirements definition.</p>

<p>The role of the QA engineer also has shifted. Now that QA is no longer saddled with functional testing, they can focus on more value-added testing like looking for edge cases, exploratory and integration testing. Together with the shift of responsibilities, is the shift on core skills of the QA; now, they can also code. The ability to speak the same language with the development team is a big time saver.</p>

<p>The traditional QA task of manual testing has not gone away. It is still as important today as it was then. While we took great strides in automated testing, it cannot tell us the whole story. Automated testing cannot tell us if we built the right thing; it can only tell us that we built the thing right; this is why we still bookend the sprints with manual and usability testing.</p>

<p>It is good to include Product Owners in the manual testing phase, in fact, it should be part of their responsibilities. This phase of testing is an excellent time to focus on what matters most to the biggest stakeholders (the users). In the absence of a Product Owner, the QA engineer can step into this role.</p>

<p>The Agile practices has resulted to tremendous benefits in code delivery. It made the development team nimbler and more responsive to changing business needs. The QA and development teams will continually evolve, up until the point where their responsibilities  are combined; clearly, that is where we are headed now.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sdlc" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Software testing remains a very important and integral part of software development. Before the advent of Agile practices, software testing was, an afterthought; it’s something that we do right after coding finishes. We’ve come a long way from that. Some teams even write the tests first, before writing the actual codes. The tests not only serve as a gatekeeper for releases, but more importantly, they also serve as an important documentation for the code.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/agile.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/agile.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Android Jetpack UI Navigation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/android/2018/11/24/android-navigation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Android Jetpack UI Navigation" /><published>2018-11-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-11-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/android/2018/11/24/android-navigation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/android/2018/11/24/android-navigation.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="how-android-jetpack-navigation-saved-us-from-our-own-fragments">How Android Jetpack Navigation Saved Us From Our Own Fragments</h2>

<p>Imagine you’re planning a road trip across a small country. You’ve got a car, a map, and a playlist. Everything’s fine—until someone tells you that every time you stop for gas, you need to rebuild the car from scratch, and remember exactly how to reattach the doors in the right order.</p>

<p>That, roughly, was Android navigation before Jetpack came along.</p>

<h2 id="once-upon-a-fragment-transaction">Once Upon a Fragment Transaction</h2>

<p>In the old days, navigation in Android apps was like juggling plates while debugging a relationship. Every screen was a Fragment, and every transition between screens involved a delicate ritual called a fragment transaction.</p>

<p>You’d write something like:</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">supportFragmentManager</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">beginTransaction</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">replace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">R</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">container</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nc">DetailsFragment</span><span class="p">())</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">addToBackStack</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">null</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">commit</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>You might not know what this code does, but that’s fine — sometimes we weren’t entirely sure either.</p>

<p>It worked, mostly. But the more screens you added, the more your app started to feel like a Jenga tower built entirely out of NullPointerExceptions. You’d tap “Back,” and suddenly the app would teleport you to a screen you swore you’d deleted last week.</p>

<p>We had conventions to survive the chaos — “always call commitNow() here,” or “never use replace, only hide and show,” or “just rewrite it, it’s faster.” Entire Stack Overflow threads were written in the tone of war diaries.</p>

<h2 id="enter-jetpack-the-gps-for-our-app">Enter Jetpack: The GPS for Our App</h2>

<p>Google looked at this situation and said, “What if we just gave developers a map?”</p>

<p>That’s where Jetpack Navigation came from. It’s a system that says, “Instead of manually wiring your app like a Christmas tree, just tell me what the destinations are and how they connect. I’ll handle the wiring.”</p>

<p>It introduced three simple ideas:</p>

<p>A navigation graph — like a subway map of your app’s screens.</p>

<p>A NavHost — the thing that actually shows one “station” at a time.</p>

<p>A NavController — the conductor that knows where you are and where you’re going.</p>

<p>In short, Jetpack Navigation turns the spaghetti of fragment transactions into a clean flowchart. You focus on the journey, not the junction boxes.</p>

<h2 id="so-what-problem-does-it-actually-solve">So What Problem Does It Actually Solve?</h2>

<p>Let’s be honest: building apps with multiple screens sounds simple in theory.</p>

<p>Home screen</p>

<p>Details screen</p>

<p>Settings screen</p>

<p>You’d think connecting them is just a matter of “open this when that button is pressed.”
But Android navigation has state. When the screen rotates, or the user presses Back, or the system reclaims memory, your app is expected to gracefully pick up where it left off.</p>

<p>Before Jetpack Navigation, you handled all that yourself — the back stack, fragment lifecycles, argument passing, deep links, and whatever magic makes the “Up” button behave differently from “Back.”</p>

<p>Jetpack Navigation said, “Stop. I’ll take it from here.”
It keeps track of your screens, remembers where you’ve been, and helps your app not collapse in existential confusion when the user rotates the phone mid-transition.</p>

<h2 id="the-new-way-navigating-without-losing-your-mind">The New Way: Navigating Without Losing Your Mind</h2>

<p>Here’s what it looks like now, using Kotlin and Jetpack Compose (the modern Android UI toolkit).</p>

<p>You start with a navigation graph — but instead of drawing it on a whiteboard and forgetting about it, you define it in code:</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nd">@Composable</span>
<span class="k">fun</span> <span class="nf">MyApp</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">navController</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nf">rememberNavController</span><span class="p">()</span>

    <span class="nc">NavHost</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">navController</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">startDestination</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"home"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nf">composable</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"home"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nc">HomeScreen</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">navController</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="nf">composable</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"details/{userId}"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">backStack</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span>
            <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">userId</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">backStack</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">arguments</span><span class="o">?.</span><span class="nf">getString</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"userId"</span><span class="p">)</span>
            <span class="nc">DetailsScreen</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">userId</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>That’s it. One host, a few routes, and you’re good to go.
When you want to move from one screen to another:</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">navController</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">navigate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"details/42"</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>That’s literally it. No more opening ceremonies with fragment managers.</p>

<h2 id="but-waitwe-used-to-do-all-this-by-hand">But Wait—We Used to Do All This by Hand!</h2>

<p>Yes, and we were proud of it.</p>

<p>Before Jetpack Navigation, if you wanted to open a details screen and pass a user ID, you had to:</p>

<p>Create a new Fragment.</p>

<p>Manually bundle your arguments.</p>

<p>Begin a transaction.</p>

<p>Replace the current fragment.</p>

<p>Add it to the back stack.</p>

<p>Pray to the gods of IllegalStateException.</p>

<p>And when the user pressed back? You’d have to make sure your back stack made sense, that your toolbar’s “up” button did something logical, and that your fragments weren’t secretly nesting fragments inside fragments (which, if you’ve ever tried, is like storing a cat inside another cat).</p>

<p>Jetpack Navigation replaced all that with a clear flow. You say what should happen (“go to details”), not how it should happen (“remove current fragment, commit transaction, etc.”).</p>

<p>It’s the difference between telling your car “drive to the store” versus personally managing the engine timing and air-fuel ratio.</p>

<p>Arguments, But Without the Arguing</p>

<p>Passing data between screens used to be a small act of ceremony. You’d bundle arguments, unpack them on the other side, and discover at runtime that you misspelled the key.</p>

<p>With Jetpack Navigation, arguments are part of the route:</p>

<p>composable(“details/{userId}”) { backStack -&gt;
    val userId = backStack.arguments?.getString(“userId”)
    DetailsScreen(userId)
}</p>

<p>Now your navigation graph doubles as documentation. You can see at a glance that “details” expects a userId. No magic strings, no guesswork, no debugging at 2 a.m. because “userID” (capital D) didn’t match “userId” (lowercase d).</p>

<h2 id="the-back-stack-tamed-at-last">The Back Stack, Tamed at Last</h2>

<p>Back navigation used to be… unpredictable.
Press back too many times and you’d exit the app. Press it once and—surprise—you’re on a screen from three screens ago.</p>

<p>Jetpack Navigation keeps track of where you’ve been. It automatically pops the right screen when you go back, like a polite doorman who remembers where you came from.</p>

<p>You can even control it precisely:</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">navController</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">navigate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"home"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nf">popUpTo</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"login"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">inclusive</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">true</span> <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This says, “Go to home, but remove everything up to and including login.” Perfect for finishing an onboarding flow without letting the user accidentally backtrack into the signup page from 20 minutes ago.</p>

<h2 id="and-because-its-2025-deep-links-too">And Because It’s 2025: Deep Links Too</h2>

<p>Jetpack Navigation also understands URLs.
If you define a deep link like myapp://details/42, the system can open the app right at that screen, skipping the rest. It’s like having a cheat code for navigation.</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nf">composable</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="s">"details/{userId}"</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="n">deepLinks</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nf">listOf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">navDeepLink</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">uriPattern</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"myapp://details/{userId}"</span> <span class="p">})</span>
<span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">backStack</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span>
    <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">userId</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">backStack</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">arguments</span><span class="o">?.</span><span class="nf">getString</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"userId"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nc">DetailsScreen</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">userId</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Suddenly, “open from notification” or “open from web link” just works.
No more launching the wrong screen because your Intent forgot an extra.</p>

<h2 id="why-it-matters">Why It Matters</h2>

<p>You could build an app without Jetpack Navigation. Many people still do, and that’s fine.
But if you’ve ever tried to fix a bug in an app with five fragments and no consistent back stack rules, you’ll know why Navigation exists.</p>

<p>It’s not about saving time (though it does that too). It’s about having a system that thinks about your app the same way you do — as a flow, not a pile of screens.</p>

<p>The code looks cleaner. The logic reads like a story. And when your teammate opens your project six months later, they won’t have to summon ancient Stack Overflow posts to understand how back navigation works.</p>

<h2 id="the-moral-of-the-story">The Moral of the Story</h2>

<p>Jetpack Navigation didn’t invent navigation. It just made it human.</p>

<p>It took a task that used to involve arcane rituals and replaced it with a simple idea:
tell Android where you want to go, not how to drive there.</p>

<p>And that’s how a small library quietly rescued thousands of developers from their own fragments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="android" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Android Jetpack Navigation Saved Us From Our Own Fragments]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/android/images/uinavigation.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/android/images/uinavigation.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kotlin Collections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/working-with-kotlin-collections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kotlin Collections" /><published>2018-10-17T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-10-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/kotlin-collections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/working-with-kotlin-collections/"><![CDATA[<p>The Kotlin collections are actually direct instances of the collections in the JDK. There’s no conversion of wrapping involved. So, if you didn’t skimp on your study of collections while you were in Java, that will certainly come in handy now.  Although Kotlin didn’t define its own collections code, it did add quite a few convenience functions to the framework, which is a welcome addition because it makes the collections easier to work with.</p>

<p>Before we go to the code examples and more details, something needs to be said why it is called a collections framework. The reason it’s called a framework is because the data structures are very diverse, in and of themselves. Some of them puts constraints on how we go through the collection, they impose certain order of traversal. Some of the collections constrains the uniqueness of the data elements, they won’t allow you to put duplicates. And some of them lets us work with the collections in pairs, like in a dictionary entry, you’ll have a key with a corresponding value.</p>

<p>.At the top of the hierarchy are the interfaces <em>Iterable</em> and <em>MutableIterable</em> —  refer to the big image at the beginning of this article. They are the parents of all the collection classes we will work with. As you may have noticed in the diagram, each Java collection has two representations in Kotlin; a read-only one and a mutable one. The mutable interfaces map directly to the Java interfaces while the immutable interfaces lack all of the mutator methods of their mutable counterparts.</p>

<p>Kotlin doesn’t have a dedicated syntax for creating lists or sets, but it does provide us with library functions to facilitate creation. Table 1 lists some of them.</p>

<p><em>Table 1. creation functions for collections</em></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Collection</th>
      <th>read only</th>
      <th>read-write</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>list</td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">listOf</code></td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mutableListOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">arrayListOf</code></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>set</td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">setOf</code></td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mutableSetOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hashSetOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linkedSetOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sortedSetOf</code></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>map</td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mapOf</code></td>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mutableMapOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hashMapOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">linkedMapOf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sortedMapOf</code></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>NOTE</strong> Although the map class doesn’t inherit from either Iterable or MutableIterable (Figure 6-1), it’s still represented in Kotlin as two distinct versions, a mutable and an immutable one.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="list">List</h1>

<p>A list is a type of collection that has a specific iteration order.  It means that if we added a couple of elements to the list, and then we step through it, the elements would come out in a very specific order — it’s the order by which they were added or inserted.  They won’t come out in a random order or reverse chronology, but precisely in the sequence they were added.  It implies that each element in the list has a placement order, an index number that indicates its ordinal position. The first element to be added will have its index at 0, the second will be 1, the third will be 2, so on and so forth. So, just like an array, it is zero-based</p>

<h1 id="set">Set</h1>

<p>Sets are very similar to lists, both in operation and in structure, so, all of the things we’ve learned about lists applies to sets as well. Sets differ from lists in the way it puts constraints on the uniqueness of elements.  It doesn’t allow duplicate elements or the same elements within a set. It may seem obvious to many what the “same” means, but Kotlin, like Java has a specific meaning for “sameness”.  When we say that two objects are the same, it means that we’ve subjected the objects to a test for structural equality. Both Java and Kotlin defines a method called equals() which allows us to determine equivalence relationships between objects.  This is generally what we mean by “sameness”. </p>

<h1 id="map">Map</h1>

<p>Unlike lists or sets, maps aren’t a collection of individual values, but rather, they are a collection of pairs of values. Think of a map like a dictionary or a phone book, its contents are organized using a key-value pair. For each key in a map, there is one and only one corresponding value.  In a dictionary example, the key would be the <em>term</em>, and its value would be the <em>meaning</em> or the <em>definition</em> of the term.</p>

<p>The keys in a map is unique. Like sets, maps do not allow duplicate keys. However, the values in a map are not subjected to the same uniqueness constraints , two or more pairs in map may have the same value</p>

<h1 id="collection-protocols">Collection Protocols</h1>

<p>The Kotlin team probably didn’t refer to the set of actions you can do on collections as “collections protocol”, I just thought it would be cool to borrow the term from Python . Anyhoo, one of the benefits of working with the collections framework is that, your knowledge and skill on lists, for example, commutes nicely to sets and maps. This way, you learn a set of skills for one kind of collection and you can use it on the other two. This is one of the reasons it’s called a framework.</p>

<p><em>Table 2. Common things you can find or do in the collection classes</em></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>function or property</th>
      <th>description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">size</code></td>
      <td>tells you how many elements are in the collection.  Works with lists, sets and maps</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">isEmpty()</code></td>
      <td>returns True if the collection is empty, False if it’s not.  Works with lists, sets and maps</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">contains(arg)</code></td>
      <td>returns True if arg is within the collection. Works with lists, sets and maps</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">add(arg)</code></td>
      <td>add arg to the collection. This function returns true if arg was added — in the case of a list,  arg will always be added. In the case of a set, arg will be added and return true the first time, but if the same arg is added the second time, it will return False. This member function is not found on maps</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">remove(arg)</code></td>
      <td>returns True if arg was removed from the collection, returns False is the collection is unmodified</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">iterator()</code></td>
      <td>returns an iterator over the elements of the object. This was inherited from the Iterable interface. Works with lists, sets and maps</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h1 id="traversing-collections">Traversing collections</h1>

<p>The Collections class inherits from the Iterable interface. That means all Collections classes is also an Iterable object. What that means is, we can get an iterator object from a Collections class.   An iterator lets us step through the elements of an object. In each step, the value of the element is exposed to us, we can use in whatever way we want e.g. assign it to a variable, transform it or store it somewhere else, etc.</p>

<p>Sample code below shows how to create an immutable list of Strings and walk through each of  its elements.  You’ve probably done quite a lot of these when you wer coding in Java</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">basket</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nf">listOf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"apple"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"banana"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"orange"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">iter</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">basket</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">iterator</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="k">while</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">iter</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">hasNext</span><span class="p">())</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">iter</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">next</span><span class="p">())</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="k">for</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">i</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="n">basket</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The sample code below is another way of traversing the same list of Strings, but this example uses the <em>forEach</em> function. This is a lot shorter, and is the preferred way, some people would even say, idiomatic way, of working with Kotlin collections.</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">fruits</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">it</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">}</span>  
</code></pre></div></div>

<h1 id="filter-function">Filter function</h1>

<p>Kotlin’s filter function is a super handy tool for dealing with groups of things (like lists). It lets you easily pick out only the items you want, based on some simple rule. It’s basically an easy way to sort the good stuff from the rest.</p>

<p>How filter Works
You start with a list of things. You use .filter on it and tell it your rule.</p>

<pre><code class="language-kotline">val newList = oldList.filter { item -&gt; your_rule }
</code></pre>

<p>It checks every single item in the old list against your rule:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If the rule says true (Yes, keep it!), the item goes into the new list.</li>
  <li>If the rule says false (Nope, toss it!), the item is left behind.</li>
</ul>

<p>The big thing to remember: filter never changes the first list. It always makes a brand new list with just the keepers.</p>

<h2 id="a-quick-how-to">A Quick How-To</h2>

<p>Let’s say you have a list of numbers.</p>

<p><strong>1. Start with a List</strong>
Kotlin</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">numbers</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nf">listOf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">12</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">8</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">21</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>2. Make Your Rule</strong></p>

<p>Say you only want numbers that are bigger than 7.</p>

<p><strong>3. Use filter</strong></p>

<p>We use the simple word it inside the curly braces to mean “the current item being checked.”</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">bigNumbers</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">numbers</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">filter</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">it</span> <span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">7</span> <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="c1">// The rule 'it &gt; 7' is true for 12, 8, and 21.</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>4. Check the Result</strong>
The bigNumbers list now only has those three:</p>

<pre><code class="language-Kotlin">println(bigNumbers) // Output: [12, 8, 21]
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Fun with People</strong></p>

<p>You can do this with more than just numbers. Imagine you have a list of people, each with an age.</p>

<pre><code class="language-Kotlin">data class Person(val name: String, val age: Int)
val friends = listOf(Person("Alice", 25), Person("Bob", 35), Person("Charlie", 28))

// Find friends who are under 30 years old.
val youngFriends = friends.filter { it.age &lt; 30 }
// Result: Alice and Charlie
</code></pre>

<p>It’s a clean way to keep your code easy to read and simple to use! There are also simple versions like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">filterNotNull</code> if you just need to drop the items that are null (nothing).</p>

<h1 id="map-function">Map function</h1>

<p>There will be times when, you don’t just want to filter a list and keep some stuff; you want to change everything in the list and get a brand-new list back. That’s where Kotlin’s map function comes in handy. It’s the perfect tool for taking a list of one thing and turning it into a list of something totally different. 🔄</p>

<p><strong>What <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">map</code> Does</strong></p>

<p>Think of map like an assembly line. You start with a list of items on one end, and you tell the “machine” (the map function) exactly what to do to each item as it passes by. It takes the result of that change and puts it on a new list on the other end.</p>

<p>It follows a simple pattern:</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">newList</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">oldList</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">map</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">item</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">the_change_you_make_to_it</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It checks every single item in the old list, makes a change, and then puts the changed result into the new list. Just like filter, it never changes the first list; it only ever makes a new one.</p>

<p><strong>Step-by-Step with an Example</strong></p>

<p>Let’s say you have a list of numbers, and you want to know what each number would be if you doubled it.</p>

<p><strong>1. Start with a List</strong></p>

<pre><code class="language-Kotlin">val scores = listOf(5, 10, 4, 8)
</code></pre>

<p><strong>2. Define the Change</strong></p>

<p>The rule is: take the current item and multiply it by two.</p>

<p><strong>3. Use map</strong></p>

<p>We use the simple word it inside the curly braces to mean “the current item being looked at.”</p>

<pre><code class="language-Kotlin">val doubleScores = scores.map { it * 2 }
</code></pre>

<p>Kotlin does this for every item:</p>

<ul>
  <li>5 becomes 10</li>
  <li>10 becomes 20</li>
  <li>4 becomes 8</li>
  <li>8 becomes 16</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>4. Check the Result</strong></p>

<p>The doubleScores list is a brand-new list with the results of your change:</p>

<pre><code class="language-Kotlin">println(doubleScores) // Output: [10, 20, 8, 16]
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Changing Types of Things</strong></p>

<p>The cool part is you can change the type of thing you have. Say you have a list of Person objects with names and you just want a list of their names as strings:</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="kd">data class</span> <span class="nc">Person</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">name</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">String</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">age</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">Int</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">friends</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nf">listOf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Person</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Alice"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">25</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nc">Person</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Bob"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">35</span><span class="p">))</span>

<span class="c1">// We turn the list of Person objects into a list of just their names (Strings).</span>
<span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">names</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">friends</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">map</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">it</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">name</span> <span class="p">}</span>

<span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">names</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// Output: [Alice, Bob]</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">map</code> keeps your code clean and simple, helping you quickly change whole lists of data without writing tons of extra steps. Neat!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="kotlin" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Kotlin collections are actually direct instances of the collections in the JDK. There’s no conversion of wrapping involved. So, if you didn’t skimp on your study of collections while you were in Java, that will certainly come in handy now. Although Kotlin didn’t define its own collections code, it did add quite a few convenience functions to the framework, which is a welcome addition because it makes the collections easier to work with.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/kotlin-collections-classes.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/kotlin-collections-classes.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">If I have a Delorean</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/if-i-have-a-delorean/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="If I have a Delorean" /><published>2018-10-05T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-10-05T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/if-i-have-a-delorean</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/if-i-have-a-delorean/"><![CDATA[<p>There was discussion post in <strong>dev.to</strong> <a href="https://dev.to/sergiotapia/what-is-your-best-advice-for-a-junior-software-developer-32gn">what is your best advise for a junior software developer</a>. I ended up responding with a 15-item, somewhat tongue-in-cheek, advise. Here they are;</p>

<p>If I have Doc Brown’s DeLorean, this is what I would advise my younger self;</p>

<ol>
  <li>Keep your head down during code reviews. Humility goes a long way. They’re not criticizing you, it’s your code they’re after. It’s not personal</li>
  <li>Do the required reading before you get knee-deep in the code. You have a propensity to shoot from the hip, curb that enthusiasm. Don’t read the manual only when you’re in trouble</li>
  <li>Design patterns are nice, but you don’t have to use all of them, all the time in every code you write</li>
  <li>Learn Python early. Get to the Python REPL and type <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">import this</code>. Learn it by heart, then read no. 3 (above) again</li>
  <li>Coffee, pizza and chips are nice now, but 20 years from now, you’re gonna wish you didn’t eat those</li>
  <li>In a couple of years, social media is gonna be big. Stay out of it</li>
  <li>Those math subjects you hated, better get more comfortable with them. There’s gonna be a thing called “machine learning”, it’s gonna be big, you’re gonna need them maths</li>
  <li>Stop wondering when you will graduate from being a junior, you’ll know it when you’re out of it. When you start making technical choices and you recognize that there are choices to be made; then you’re not so junior anymore</li>
  <li>Be polite when asking questions. If you don’t want to get the RTFM response (a lot), read Eric Raymond’s guide on <a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">how to ask smart questions</a></li>
  <li>When you’re tech lead or any of your bosses calls you for a meeting, always bring a pen and paper. Write your notes</li>
  <li>If it’s taking you more than 3 hours to figure out something, ask for help, tell your tech lead what’s eating you up (but make sure that before you do this, you’ve read no. 9 above)</li>
  <li>If you promised your tech lead (client, coworker or boss) you will deliver the thing on Friday, and you’re not gonna make it, tell them early. Don’t tell them on Friday</li>
  <li>Exercise. You’re brain (and your blood pressure) will love you for it</li>
  <li>When the book “Pragmatic programmer, journeyman to master” comes out. Read it</li>
  <li>From time to time, write a program in LOLCODE, don’t lose your humor</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="dev," /><category term="career" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[if you can go back in time, what will you advise your younger self; a junior developer]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/backtothefuture.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/backtothefuture.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Learn Android Studio 3 Kotlin</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/learn-android-studio3-kotlin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learn Android Studio 3 Kotlin" /><published>2018-10-04T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-10-04T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/learn-android-studio-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/learn-android-studio3-kotlin/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s finally here. Learn Android Studio 3 with Kotlin is available. You can get it from <a class="inline-button" href="https://www.apress.com/gp/book/9781484239063" target="_blank">Apress website</a> or from <a class="inline-button" href="https://www.amazon.com/Learn-Android-Studio-Kotlin-Development/dp/1484239067/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1539340099&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=learn+android+studio+3+with+kotlin" target="_blank">Amazon</a>.</p>

<p>The Kotlin edition is roughly 100+ pages thicker than the Java edition. It has more worked examples than the previous edition. BTW, it isn’t (just) about Android Studio; the book has 3 learning curves, 1) Android SDK 2) Kotlin and 3) Android Studio. Chapters 1-7 are about Kotlin and chapters 8-20 are about Android programming (SDK). So, it’s a good introductory book if you’re new to Kotlin or Android programming.</p>

<h2 id="chapter-overviews">Chapter overviews</h2>

<p><strong>Chapter 1</strong> “Getting into Kotlin” introduces the language. It tells you how to setup Kotlin in various ways on the 3 major platforms macOS, Linux and Windows.  It also contains instructions on how to create, configure and run a project in IntelliJ — this is the IDE I used to create all the Kotlin code samples for chapters 1-7.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 2</strong> “Kotlin Basics” dives into the language fundamentals of Kotlin. You’ll learn the basic building blocks of a Kotlin program e.g. Strings, control structures, exception handling, basic data types. You’ll also see some of Kotlin’s features that are very different from Java, like it’s treatment of nullable and non-nullable types.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 3</strong> “Functions”. There’s a whole chapter dedicated to functions because Kotlin’s functions have something new up its sleeves. It has all the trimmings of a modern language like default and named parameters, infix functions and operators; and with Kotlin, we can also create extension functions. Extension functions lets you add behavior to and existing class, without inheriting from it and without changing its source</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 4</strong> “Working with Types”. This chapter deals with object-oriented topics. You’ll learn how Kotlin treats interfaces, classes and access modifiers. We’ll also learn about the new <em>data classes</em> in Kotlin. It also talks about <em>object declarations</em> — it’s the replacement for Java’s <em>static</em> keyword.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 5</strong> “Lambdas and Higher Order Functions”.  Now we go to Kotlins’s functional programming capabilities. It discusses how to create and use higher-order functions, lambdas and closures.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 6</strong> “Collections” walks through the classic collection classes of Java and how to use them in Kotlin.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 7</strong> “Generics”. Using generics in Kotlin isn’t that much different in Java. If generics is old hat for you, then most of this chapter will be a review. But try to read through it still because it talks about <em>reified generics</em>, which Java doesn’t have.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 8</strong> “Android Studio Introduction and Setup”.  Talks a bit about Android’s history, its technical make-up and the OS. It also walks you through the installation and setup of Android Studio.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 9</strong> “Getting Started” gets you grounded on the fundamental concepts about Android programming. It talks about components, what they are, how they are organized and come together in an Android app. In this chapter, you’ll learn how the basic workflow of an Android project — how to create a project and run it on an emulator</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 10</strong> “Activities and Layouts”. Here, we’ll learn how to build a UI. Activity, Layout and View objects are the building blocks for an Android UI.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 11</strong> “Event Handling”. You’ll learn how to react to user-generated events like clicks and longclicks. We’ll use some concepts that we learned in Chapter 4 and 5 (inner objects and lambdas) to help us write more compact and succinct event-handling code.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 12</strong> “Intents”.  This chapter reviews some fundamental concepts on Android programming, specifically the concept of components; which dovetails to the topic of Intents. You’ll learn how to use Intents to launch another Activity and pass data in-and-around Activities</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 13</strong> “Themes and Menus”. This is a short chapter. You’ll learn how to add styles/themes to your app. We’ll also work with some menus and the ActionBar.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 14</strong> “Fragments”.  You’ll learn how to use Android Fragments as a more granular composition unit for UI. We’ll also see how to use Fragments to address changes in device orientation.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 15</strong> “Running in the background”. Any non-trivial app will do something substantial like read from a file, write to a file, download something from the network. These activities will likely take more than 16ms to execute (you’ll learn why 16ms should be the upper limit and why you should not exceed it). When that happens, the user will see and feel “jank”.  This chapter discusses the various ways on how to run our code in a background thread.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 16</strong> “Debugging” shows some of the things you can do to debug your apps in Android Studio 3. It goes through a list of the kinds of errors you might encounter while coding and what you can do in Android Studio to respond them</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 17</strong> “SharedPreferences”. When you need to save simple data, you can use the SharedPreferences API. This chapter walks you through detailed examples on how to do that.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 18</strong> “Internal Storage”. Just like in SharedPreferences, you can also store data using the Internal Storage API of Android. This chapter discusses internal and external storage</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 19</strong> “BroadcastReceivers”. Android has a way to make highly-decoupled components talk to each other. This chapter talks about how BroadcastReceivers can facilitate messaging for Android components.</p>

<p><strong>Chapter 20</strong> “App Distribution”. When you’re ready to distribute your app, you’ll need to sign it and list it in a marketplace like Google Play. This chapter walks you through the steps on how to do it</p>

<h2 id="about-the-author">About the author</h2>

<p>Ted has been in software development for 20+ years. He’s a developer by trade, at the moment he’s the CTO and DPO of RenditionDigital International, a software development company based out of Dublin. He wrote a couple of books for Apress.</p>

<p><img src="/images/las3kotlinwhite.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Get it from the <a class="inline-button" href="https://www.apress.com/gp/book/9781484239063" target="_blank">Apress website</a> or from <a class="inline-button" href="https://www.amazon.com/Learn-Android-Studio-Kotlin-Development/dp/1484239067/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1539340099&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=learn+android+studio+3+with+kotlin" target="_blank">Amazon</a>. Thanks!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="android," /><category term="kotlin" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This book has an introduction to Kotlin, Android Programming and of course, Android Studio IDE]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/las3kotlincover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/las3kotlincover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Started in Kotlin</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/kotlin-getting-started/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Started in Kotlin" /><published>2018-08-15T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-08-15T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/kotlin-getting-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/kotlin-getting-started/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s the new(est) kid on the the JVM  block.</p>

<p>It’s from JetBrains, they’re the guys who built IntelliJ. They’ve been around for quite some time, so chances are you already know them. Kotlin has also been around for quite sometime, since 2011 in fact — it gained a lot of traction and attention probably 2016 or 2017 (I’m not sure, I’m too lazy to research).  The “hooray” moment for Kotlin was probably during Google I/O 2017, because they (Google) announced that it can now be used for Android programming. This was the same time that Android Studio 3 was about to be released, and AS3 already has an out-of-the-box support for Kotlin. You don’t even have to add the plugin anymore.</p>

<p>Like Java, Kotlin is;</p>

<ul>
  <li>compiled</li>
  <li>statically typed, but we don’t always have to write the type. Kotlin can infer types on most situations. When Java 10 comes out, it will be able to infer types too, at least for local variables</li>
  <li>strongly typed</li>
  <li>object oriented</li>
</ul>

<p>Unlike Java, it;</p>

<ul>
  <li>treats functions as first class citizens and it supports functional programming. We also can write functions as top-level constructs, it doesn’t have to be inside a class anymore. Kotlin refers functions inside a class as member functions, not member methods</li>
  <li>treats exceptions differently. All exceptions are unchecked exceptions, you may (or may not) handle exceptions, it’s up to you and not the compiler. try-catch blocks are optional</li>
  <li>doesn’t have primitive types, everything truly is, an object</li>
  <li>doesn’t have static members</li>
  <li>treats everything as public by default, classes, variables and functions. If you want to restrict accessibility, you’ll have to specify it</li>
  <li>treats expressions and statements differently, e.g. assignment is a statement in Kotlin (it is an expression in Java), the decision making constructs like <em>if</em> and <em>when</em> are expressions, not statements</li>
  <li>treats all variables as <em>non-Nullable</em> by default. It means, when you declare a variable in Kotlin, without any decoration, modifier or annotation, the variable can never be assigned a <em>null</em> value</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="compilation">Compilation</h1>

<p>It’s a JVM language, so, naturally, you still need the JDK. KT files are compiled using the kotlin compiler (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">kotlinc</code>).</p>

<p><img src="/images/kotlin-compilation-process.png" alt="compilation process" /></p>

<p>The Kotlin compiler outputs <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.class</code> files, just like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">javac</code>. But, you cannot run Kotlin bytecodes the same way you would run Java bytecodes. You’ll need to combine the resulting  Kotlin byte code with the Kotlin runtime and package it into a jar file. Only then will you be able to run the program.</p>

<p>This detail is probably important for you if you will work with Kotlin on the command line. These compilation and execution details are typically handled for you by an IDE.  I can think of three IDEs that should be usable with Kotlin; Eclipse, NetBeans and IntelliJ — the last one is a commercial IDE but it does have a community edition. IntelliJ CE is able to run Kotlin.  Anyone of these 3 IDEs should suffice. In case you choose to use IDEA, you might want to refer to the <a href="http://bit.ly/intellijguide">IntelliJ minimal survival guide</a>.</p>

<h1 id="project-setup-in-intellij">Project setup in IntelliJ</h1>

<p>Launch IntelliJ if it isn’t opened yet. On the “Welcome” screen, click “Create new Project”. Next, you should see a screen like Figure 1.</p>

<p><img src="/images/new-project-intellij.png" alt="newprojectidea" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1. New Project</strong></p>

<p>Choose “Kotlin/JVM”, as shown in Figure 1, and try to see if IntelliJ has detected your installed JDK. As you can see, it detected my JDK 9.</p>

<p>Next, fill out the “Project name” information, name the project “kotlinproject” for example.  After that, the project should be created and opened in IntellIJ.</p>

<p>Now we can add a Kotlin file to the project. Use the context menu (right click) on the “src” folder, as shown in Figure 2.</p>

<p><img src="/images/new-kotlin-file.png" alt="new file" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2. Add a Kotlin file to the project</strong></p>

<p>Choose “Kotlin/File”. Name the file, and you should be good to go.</p>

<h1 id="hello-world">Hello World</h1>

<p>The simplest program we’ll create in Kotlin could look like the following;</p>

<p><strong>Listing 1. hello.Kt</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">fun</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">Array</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="nc">String</span><span class="p">&gt;)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Hello"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Kotlin programs don’t need classes in order to run. You can get by with top level functions only.</p>

<p>To run this code in IntelliJ, from the main menu bar, click <strong>Run</strong> →  <strong>Run</strong>. You will notice that there are two Run options on the menu. The first Run is greyed out. That’s because we haven’t defined any runtime configuration yet. Choose the second Run option. You should see a popup dialog, as shown in Figure 3</p>

<p><img src="/images/kotlin-run-context.png" alt="new file" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 3. Running Hello.Kt</strong></p>

<h1 id="variables">Variables</h1>

<p>Variables are declared either as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> or as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">var</code>.  Listing 2 shows some example usage</p>

<p><strong>Listing 2. Variable declarations</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">someStr</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">String</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"Hello"</span> <span class="c1">// (1) </span>
<span class="n">someStr</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"World"</span>             <span class="c1">// (2)</span>

<span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">someInt</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>               <span class="c1">// (3)</span>
<span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">anotherInt</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>            <span class="c1">// (4)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>(1)</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">someString</code> is the variable name (identifier)  and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">String</code> is the type of variable. The type is written to the right of the identifier, and they are separated by a colon. It’s  quite the reverse in Java where the type is written to the left of the identifier.</p>

<p><strong>(2)</strong> We can re-assign values to variables that were declared as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">var</code>. No surprises here.</p>

<p><strong>(3)</strong> Same as the first statement, except that were using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> instead of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">var</code>, and were not specifying the type anymore. There are many situations in Kotlin where you can skip type declaration. This case is one of those. The c0mpiler can infer the type of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">someInt</code> from the assignment. It will see that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1</code> is an Integer literal, hence, it can make the necessary type assignment</p>

<p><strong>(4)</strong> This statement won’t work because variables declared as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> are effectively constants. They become immutable. The Java equivalent is when you declare a variable as <em>final</em></p>

<h1 id="types">Types</h1>

<p>There are no primitive types in Kotlin, everything is an object. So, if you need to work with numbers, the types youl’ll work with are the following; Double, Float, Long, Int, Short and Byte, their bit widths are 64, 32, 64, 32, 16 and 8, respectively — that might be easier to look at in table form, so here you go.</p>

<p><strong>Table 1. built-in number types</strong></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Type</th>
      <th>Bit width</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Double</td>
      <td>64</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Float</td>
      <td>32</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Long</td>
      <td>64</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Int</td>
      <td>32</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Short</td>
      <td>16</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Byte</td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>For the most part, operations on number types works the way you expect them, by that I mean, the way you expect them to work in Java. What’s different in Kotlin is that we don’t have implicit casting anymore. You can’t assign an Int to a Long, while this would have worked in Java, it doesn’t in Kotlin. If you want to convert from one type to another, you’d have to do that explicitly</p>

<p><strong>Listing 3.  No implict casting</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">a</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="mi">10L</span> <span class="c1">// a is a Long literal, note the L postfix</span>
<span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">b</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="mi">20</span>

<span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">a</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">b</span> <span class="c1">// this won’t work</span>
<span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">a</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">b</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">toLong</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="c1">// this will work</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>Characters</strong></p>

<p>You might remember from Java that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">char</code> was treated as a number, that’s not the case in Kotlin. You can’t write code’s like this</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">fun</span> <span class="nf">checkForKey</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">keyCode</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="nc">Char</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">keyCode</span> <span class="p">==</span> <span class="mi">97</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="c1">// won’t work, keyCode is not a number</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Character literals are created by using single quotes, like so</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">enterKey</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="err">‘</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="err">’</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Like in Java, you can use escape sequences such as \t, \b, \n, \r, \’, \”, \ and $ and if you need to encode any other character, you can use the Unicode syntax e.g. \uFF00.</p>

<p><strong>Booleans</strong> work and behave exactly as they do in Java. Even the literals are exactly the same — <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">false</code></p>

<h1 id="branching">Branching</h1>

<p>The  <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code> construct work almost the same as in Java.</p>

<p><strong>Listing 4. Branching with If</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">bigNum</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">firstNum</span>
<span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">secondNum</span> <span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="n">firstNum</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="n">bigNum</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">secondNum</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The second form, with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else</code> is written as follows.</p>

<p><strong>Listing 5. If Else construct</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">bigNum</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">Int</span>
<span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">secondNum</span> <span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="n">firstNum</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="n">bigNum</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">secondNum</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
<span class="k">else</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="n">bigNum</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">firstNum</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The difference in Kotlin is, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code> construct is not a statement, it’s an expression. Which means we can do things like this</p>

<p><strong>Listing 6. As an expression</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">bigNum</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">firstNum</span> <span class="p">&gt;</span> <span class="n">secondNum</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="n">firstNum</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="n">secondNum</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Kotlin doesn’t have a switch statement, what it has is a <em>when</em> construct.  It’s form and structure is strikingly similar to the <em>switch</em> statement. In its simplest form, it can be implemented like this (Listing 7)</p>

<p><strong>Listing 7. Branching with When</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">d</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nc">Date</span><span class="p">()</span>
 <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">c</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="nc">Calendar</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">getInstance</span><span class="p">()</span>
 <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">day</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="n">c</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="k">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nc">Calendar</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">DAY_OF_WEEK</span><span class="p">)</span>

 <span class="k">when</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">day</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
   <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span> <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Sunday"</span><span class="p">)</span>
   <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span> <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Monday"</span><span class="p">)</span>
   <span class="mi">3</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span> <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Tuesday"</span><span class="p">)</span>
   <span class="mi">4</span> <span class="p">-&gt;</span> <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Wednesday"</span><span class="p">)</span>
 <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><em>When</em> matches the argument (the variable day) against all branches sequentially until it encounters a match; note that unlike in <em>switch</em> statements, when a match is found, it doesn’t flow through or cascade to the next branch, hence we don’t need to put a <em>break</em> statement.</p>

<h1 id="looping">Looping</h1>

<p>Kotlin also has a <em>while</em> loop, it works exactly the same in Kotlin as it does in Java.</p>

<p><strong>Listing 8. while loop</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">fun</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">Array</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="nc">String</span><span class="p">&gt;)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="py">count</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
  <span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">finish</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="mi">5</span>

  <span class="k">while</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">count</span><span class="p">++</span> <span class="p">&lt;</span> <span class="n">finish</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"counter = $count"</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Kotlin doesn’t have a <em>for</em> loop, at least not the one with the counter and incrementing variables inside. The <em>for</em> loop of Kotlin works with Iterable objects. Listing 9 shows a basic usage of the for loop.</p>

<p><strong>Listing 9. Kotlin’s for loop</strong></p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">val</span> <span class="py">words</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"The quick brown fox"</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">split</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">" "</span><span class="p">)</span>  

<span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">word</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="n">words</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>  
  <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">word</span><span class="p">)</span>  
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h1 id="functions">Functions</h1>

<p>The <em>main</em> function in Kotlin is written as follows</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">fun</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">Array</span><span class="p">&lt;</span><span class="nc">String</span><span class="p">&gt;)</span> <span class="p">{</span> 
  <span class="nf">println</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Hello"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<ul>
  <li>The keyword <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fun</code> is used to declare that the block is a function</li>
  <li>Functions names are identifiers, just like in Java. The function name <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> is special, it denotes the entry point of the program, much like the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">public static void main</code> in Java</li>
  <li>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">args</code> argument of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> is an <em>Array</em> of <em>String</em>. Kotlin doesn’t have a syntax to create arrays using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[]</code> notation. The Kotlin <em>Array</em> is a generic class, it accepts a typed parameter, it’s <em>String</em> in this case. So, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> function accepts an array of <em>String</em></li>
  <li>println is translated (under the hood) to a call to Java’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">System.out.println()</code>. Kotlin can Java codes, including the Java standard library. And likewise, Java can use codes written in Kotlin. After all, Kotlin codes translates to byte codes as well</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="default-params">Default params</h2>

<p>Function params can be assigned a default value, like this</p>

<p><strong>Listing 3-1. connectDb function</strong></p>
<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">fun</span> <span class="nf">connectDb</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">host</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">String</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"localhost"</span><span class="p">,</span>
              <span class="n">user</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">String</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"root"</span><span class="p">,</span>
              <span class="n">password</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nc">String</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">"password"</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>All the params of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">connectDb()</code> have default values, so we can call this function like this</p>

<div class="language-kotlin highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nf">connectDb</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="c1">// no arguments passed</span>
<span class="nf">connectDb</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"jupiter"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// just the 1st param</span>
<span class="nf">connectDb</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"jupiter"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">"neptune"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// 1st and 2nd params</span>
<span class="nf">connectDb</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"jupiter"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s">"neptune"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="s">"saturn"</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// or all three</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="named-params">Named params</h2>

<p>Calling functions in your code can be further improved using named parameters.</p>

<h2 id="variable-args">Variable args</h2>

<h2 id="extension-functions">Extension functions</h2>

<h2 id="infix-functions">Infix functions</h2>

<h1 id="classes-and-objects">Classes and Objects</h1>

<h1 id="access-modifiers">Access Modifiers</h1>

<h1 id="companion-objects">Companion Objects</h1>

<h1 id="higher-order-functions">Higher Order Functions</h1>

<h1 id="collections">Collections</h1>

<p>Kotlin did not build its collections framework from scratch. It actually used the existing Java Collection framework. So, Kotlin lists, sets or maps are actually the exact same list, sets and maps of Java. It’s not wrapped nor  transmogrified in any way.  But there are a couple of things we need to remember.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Each of the Java collection is represented in Kotin in two ways.</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="generics">Generics</h1>]]></content><author><name>Ted Hagos</name></author><category term="android," /><category term="kotlin" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do you want to learn Kotlin in a day? Read this.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/kotlinheader.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/kotlinheader.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Android Studio</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/android-studio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Android Studio" /><published>2018-06-03T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-06-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/android-studio-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/android-studio/"><![CDATA[<ol>
  <li>What to configure - this is part of the book</li>
  <li>Coding preferences - no need for this</li>
  <li>Common shortcuts - yes</li>
  <li>Common task you need to perform - I will do this, I will add this as part of the book
    <ol>
      <li>refactor</li>
      <li>find some thing across projects</li>
      <li>TODO lists</li>
      <li>marking blocks of code for commenting</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Project organization - yes</li>
  <li>Project settings - yes</li>
  <li>Java 10 - A small clause. yes</li>
</ol>

<p>Table 1. Common keyboard shortcuts</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Task</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Linux and Windows</strong></th>
      <th><strong>macOS</strong></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Search within a file</td>
      <td>CTRL + F</td>
      <td>⌘   + F</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Search everywhere</td>
      <td>CTRL +   Shift + F</td>
      <td>CTRL + ⌘ + F</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Save all</td>
      <td>CTLR + S</td>
      <td>⌘ + S</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Override methods</td>
      <td>CTRL + O</td>
      <td>CTRL + O</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Implement methods</td>
      <td>CTRL + I</td>
      <td>CTRL + I</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Basic code completion</td>
      <td>CTRL +   Space</td>
      <td>CTRL +   Space</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Build</td>
      <td>CTRL + F9</td>
      <td>⌘ + F9</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Build and Run</td>
      <td>Shift + F10</td>
      <td>CTRL + R</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Apply changes (with Instant Run)</td>
      <td>CTRL + F10</td>
      <td>CTRL + ⌘ + R</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>There are certain actions or option in AS3’s Main Menu that doesn’t have a default mapping to the keyboard e.g. entering a full screen view. In such cases,  you may map a keyboard shortcut of your own choosing to a menu action. You can do this in the <em>keymap settings</em> for AS3. </p>

<p><img src="/images/as3-keymap.png" alt="android studio 3 keymap" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Keymaps dropdown</strong> lets you select the desired keymap, it switches between the preset keymaps</li>
  <li><strong>Actions list</strong>. Right click on an action to modify it. You can add additional keyboard shortcuts for the action, add mouse shortcuts to associate an action with a mouse click, or remove current shortcuts. If you are using a preset keymap, modifying an action’s shortcuts will automatically create a copy of the keymap and add your modifications to the copy</li>
  <li>You can use the <strong>Search Box</strong> to search for a keyboard shortcut using the <em>action name</em></li>
  <li><strong>Search by shortcut</strong> . You can type the keyboard short cut in this search window to find the action name</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><em>Revision history</em></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>version</th>
      <th>date</th>
      <th>description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>June 4, 2018</td>
      <td>First draft</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="android" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What to configure - this is part of the book Coding preferences - no need for this Common shortcuts - yes Common task you need to perform - I will do this, I will add this as part of the book refactor find some thing across projects TODO lists marking blocks of code for commenting Project organization - yes Project settings - yes Java 10 - A small clause. yes]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/android-studio-3.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/android-studio-3.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>